<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Connor's Technical Site - Digital Logic</title><link href="https://connormonahan.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://connormonahan.net/feeds/digital-logic.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://connormonahan.net/</id><updated>2019-01-14T00:00:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>Binary, Decimal, Hexadecimal</title><link href="https://connormonahan.net/2019/01/14/binary-decimal-hexadecimal/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-01-14T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-01-14T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Connor Monahan</name></author><id>tag:connormonahan.net,2019-01-14:/2019/01/14/binary-decimal-hexadecimal/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Representation of different bases, and converting to decimal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Decimal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We think of decimal as the base-10 system. The set of all decimal digits is $\{0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9\}$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine we have a number 42 (base ten). We could rewrite it as each digit multiplied …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Representation of different bases, and converting to decimal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Decimal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We think of decimal as the base-10 system. The set of all decimal digits is $\{0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9\}$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine we have a number 42 (base ten). We could rewrite it as each digit multiplied by a power of ten, like so: $42 = 4 * 10^1 + 2 * 10^0$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Binary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The set of all binary digits is $\{0,1\}$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same idea is true for binary numbers, also known as the base-2 system. Imagine we have a number 101010 (base two). We could rewrite it as each digit multiplied by a power of two, like so: $101010_2 = 1 * 2^5 + 0 * 2^4 + 1 * 2^3 + 0 * 2^2 + 1 * 2^1 + 0 * 2^0$. If we wanted to get the decimal version of this, we could just simplify: $1 * 2^5 + 1 * 2^3 + 1 * 2^1 = 32 + 8 + 2=42$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hexadecimal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The set of all hexadecimal digits is $\{0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,A,B,C,D,E,F\}$, where A-F have decimal values of 10-15 respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same idea is true for hexadecimal numbers, also known as the base-16 system. Imagine we have a number 2A (base sixteen). We could rewrite it as each digit multiplied by a power of sixteen, like so: $2A_{16} = 2 * 16^1 + 10 * 16^0$. If we wanted to get the decimal version of this, we could just simplify: $2 * 16^1 + 10 * 16^0 = 32 + 10 = 42$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bringing it together: binary and hexadecimal to decimal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above, we have seen that finding the value of a binary or hexadecimal number in decimal simply requires writing out each digit multiplied by its place value and then simplifying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Converting decimal to binary or hexadecimal by repeated division&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A technique for converting to either binary or hexadecimal is to take the number in decimal and successively divide by either 2 or 16 (depending on the target base), using the remainders to construct the resultant number. Say we want to convert 42 to binary. We would start to divide by 2:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- thanks https://stackoverflow.com/questions/22867785 ---&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$
\require{enclose}
\begin{array}{rll}
    21\\[-3pt]
   2 \enclose{longdiv}{42}\kern-.2ex \\[-3pt]
      \underline{42}  \\[-3pt]
      0 \\[-3pt]
  \end{array}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, we know that the rightmost digit of the resulting binary number is 0, as that is the remainder of the division. We continue by dividing the previous quotient again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
\require{enclose}
\begin{array}{rll}
    10\\[-3pt]
   2 \enclose{longdiv}{21}\kern-.2ex \\[-3pt]
      \underline{20}  \\[-3pt]
      1 \\[-3pt]
  \end{array}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remainder is 1, so the next digit to the left is a 1. Continue dividing until the quotient is 0 (the intermediate three divisions are left as an exercise for the reader):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
\require{enclose}
\begin{array}{rll}
    0\\[-3pt]
   2 \enclose{longdiv}{1}\kern-.2ex \\[-3pt]
      \underline{0}  \\[-3pt]
      1 \\[-3pt]
  \end{array}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final remainder is 1, so the leftmost digit of the resulting binary number is 1. Writing all the results next to each other, we get a result of 101010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same technique works for converting to hexadecimal (simply divide by 16 repeatedly instead of 2). This technique generalizes to other bases as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>